# Rajat Prakash Singh Data Scientist

Phone: +91-8800317147 Email: rajat199292@outlook.com Location: Noida, India GitHub: rajat199292 LinkedIn: linkedin.com/in/rajatprakashsingh Kaggle: singhrajat05

#### **PROFESSIONAL SUMMARY:**

Data Science, 4+ years of broad-based experiences in building data intensive application, overcoming complex architectural, and scalability issues in diverse industries, Knowledge in data processing, data Mining algorithms and data predictive modeling, as well as scripting language, including Python and C#(.NET). Capable of creating, developing, testing and deploying highly adaptive diverse services to translate business and functional qualifications.

**EDUCATION** 

#### **Great Lakes Executive Learning, Gurugram**

May 2021 - May 2022

Post Graduate in Data Science and Business Analytics

#### Dr. A.P.J. Abdul Kalam Technical University, Uttar Pradesh

May 2012 - May 2016

Bachelor of Technology in Computer Science

## **SKILLS:**

- Technical: Algorithms, Statistics, Data Manipulation And Analysis, Data Visualization, Machine
  Learning Techniques, Quantitative Analysis, Predictive Modeling, Modeling(Classification, Regression,
  Decision Trees, K-Nearest Neighbors, Decision Trees, Hypothesis Testing, Principal Component
  Analysis (PCA), Factor Analysis, Model Fitting, Cross-Validation)
- Language: Data Structure, C++, C#, Python (Sci-kit Learn, Pandas, SciPy, NumPy)
- Databases: MS-SQL
- Tools : V S/Code, Jupyter Notebook, Tableau, Git

## **WORK EXPERIENCE:**

#### Hitachi

## **Associate Signal and Functional Engineer**

April 2019 – Present

- Increased efficiency for application program designer up to 70 % by performing descriptive analysis of error types by segregating errors into 3 groups depending on the centroid values.
- Drive the interaction and designer between the managers to ensure active cooperation in identifying as
  well as defining analytical needs and generating the insights with the business for this 60% result change
  in business.
- Build predictive models using various machine learning tools to predict the possibility of success of project.
- Develop and test of Application Data Design for more than 30 Indian railway stations, spread across five
  zones in Train Control Systems as per Railway's technical & signaling standards and Responsible for
  Verification of Application data in IFAT, CFAT and SAT for errors and Analysis, with 80% success rate.

Tool and Tech-Stack: Machine Learning, Python (Sci-kit Learn, Pandas, NumPy), MS-SQL, MS-excel, MS-doc.

## **Ajeevi Technologies**

## **Software Engineer**

May 2018 - April 2019

- Utilized individual reports and designed the final dashboard and beta dashboards to visualize
  infrastructure related incidents and jobs to meets their requirements. Performed exploratory data
  analysis while performing the ML algorithms.
- Designed and developed functional enhancements on Reporting and analytics utilizing python with ML model and achieved 20% better return in compare of historical result.
- Develop a user-friendly system for smart Bus Depot management. The module developed measures the bus km. report, bus performance, store purchase report and stock report. Developed different type of Report using C# and SQL with SSRS Report.

Tool and Tech-Stack: Python, ML, Python (Sci-kit Learn, Pandas, NumPy), MS-SQL, VStudio, Tableau (web)

# **Software Engineer**

**Sept 2017 – Dec 2017** 

- Used ML techniques on python to predict the customer most like food as per restaurants from Republiq
  app data cleaning by merging multiple datasets treating missing value followed by training the model on a
  sufficiently large amount of observation.
- Develop a Payment module with Different Payment Gateway Integration with all details required for payment gateway both (Form base and API Based), developed User invite and Business module with data driven dashboard where Marchant can see their daily report. S2S affiliate marketing In Republiq
- Creating Report using SSRS Report for Business Unit with creating some basic graph using python.

Tool and Tech-Stack: Python, ML, Python (Sci-kit Learn, Pandas, NumPy), MS-SQL, VStudio, Tableau (web)

# Ajeevi Technologies

# **Software Engineer**

June 2016 - Sept 2017

- Develop a user-friendly system for Fleet management and built different type of stored procedures and implementation of LINQ and developed analysis data driven dashboard.
- Created different type of stored procedures for data driven dashboard and developed API that is helps fetching data for apps.

Tool and Tech-Stack: Python, ML, Python (Sci-kit Learn, Pandas, NumPy), MS-SQL, VStudio, Tableau (web)

# LICENSES AND CERTIFICATIONS

- Certificate in Machine Learning in R by Collabera TACT.
- MTA in Software Fundamentals C# and MTA in Database Fundamentals.

#### **ACHIEVEMENT**

- Microsoft Student Partner 2015 and Microsoft Student Associate 2014
- Best Paper award for "Content based Image retrieval" in 11th National Conference on Next Generation
   Technologies